Guide to the Sol Stein Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Sol Stein Papers,
1943-2004
[Bulk Dates: 1950-2004].
Stein, Sol.
24.56 linear ft. (58.5 document boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY. 10027
5540444
MS#1437
The Sol Stein Papers chart the literary life of author, editor and publisher, Sol Stein, who in addition to his own career as novelist and playwright, founded the publishing house Stein and Day. His papers contain correspondence with important literary figures; multiple drafts of his plays, novels and non-fiction writing; and correspondence which closely documents the editing process. The papers also include some material relating to Stein’s political activities as Executive Director of The American Committee for Cultural Freedom and as Ideological Analyst and writer for The Voice of America.
Biographical Note
Sol Stein was born in Chicago, Illinois, on October 13, 1926 to Louis (a jewelry designer) and Zelda Stein (later a translator for the United Nations). Stein attended City College in New York but interrupted his studies to serve in the United States Army from 1945 to 1947, briefly as an infantry officer, and then as commandant of the three Occupational Training Schools in the American Zone of Germany. He was cited by Lt. General Geoffrey Keyes for having commanded the best educational units in the Third Army Area (American Zone, Germany). Stein returned to his studies and the States and earned his B.S.S. from City College, New York in 1948 and an M.A. from Columbia University the following year. While pursuing a Ph.D. at Columbia from 1949-1951, Stein lectured on social studies at City College. Despite his academic success, Stein switched gears in the early 1950s, leaving academia for the arts and joining the Voice of America's (VoA) Ideological Advisory Staff as a writer and political affairs analyst.
Established in 1942 as part of the Office of War Information, the VoA's initial mandate was to use radio broadcasts to convey accurate and balanced news to an audience abroad, eventually in forty-six languages. Its inaugural broadcast on February 24th 1942 promised that: "The news may be good. The news may be bad. We shall tell you the truth." After the War, the State Department took over responsibility for the organization. By the time Stein joined in 1951, the VoA had carved a new niche for itself as an information agency to counter and challenge Soviet propaganda in Western Europe, Asia and South America, which was gaining success in the burgeoning Cold War with the Soviet Union. By the early 1950s, broadcasts tended to be more subjective in nature and frequently anti-Communist in tone. Bolstered by the Smith-Mundt Act of 1948, which encouraged the dissemination abroad of information about the United States through media, Congress used VoA to promote American foreign policy and democracy. The broadcasts that Stein wrote from 1951-1953 examined contemporary controversies through an anti-Communist lens.
This ideological conviction was also apparent in Stein's involvement with The American Committee for Cultural Freedom (ACCF). A committee of about three hundred prominent intellectuals and artists, the ACCF was founded as the American branch of the International Congress for Cultural Freedom and notable members included W.H. Auden, Elia Kazan, Lionel Trilling, Saul Bellow, Norman Thomas, George Balanchine, Alexander Calder, and Jackson Pollack. It undertook civil rights activities as well as the organization of anti-Soviet campaigns and programs, principally acting in opposition to Senator Joseph McCarthy’s tactics and on behalf of other civil liberties issues. The organization sponsored a book written jointly by a Democrat and Republican called McCarthy and the Communists, which was on the New York Times best-seller list for thirteen weeks and was widely influential. Stein was appointed Executive Director in 1953 and his involvement with the organization ranged from organizing discussion panels of prominent intellectuals, frequent communication with news media, and countering government stupidities like barring American professors of Soviet history from receiving Russian newspapers. The committee possibly saved the lives of two men, a Russian sailor who abandoned ship in New York Harbor and Hasan Muhammad Tiro, who was tried and sentenced to death in absentia in his native Indonesia while a graduate student at Columbia University and was rescued by a telephone call from Norman Thomas, a director of the Committee, to President Eisenhower. Stein resigned in 1956 and the Committee disbanded the following year.
Stein began to carve a name for himself as a literary writer in the early 1950s. While writing for The New Leader, Commentary, The New Republic and The Christian Science Monitor, Stein was also establishing himself as a playwright. His 1953 play Napoleon, staged at the American National Theatre and Academy, won the Dramatists Alliance Prize for best full-length play of 1953. Alongside Elia Kazan, Tennessee William sand William Inge, Stein was one of the founding members of the Playwright's Group at the Actor's Studio. Stein's other staged works include A Shadow of My Enemy (1957) and Of Love and Marriage (1964). Stein also worked in academia and publishing through the 1950s and 1960s, lecturing on drama at Columbia and working as a general editor for Beacon Press from 1954-1957. At Beacon Press, he invented the book-size paperback which became and remains the standard form for upscale paperback books. In addition, he published a series of short hardcover essays dealing with contemporary cultural concerns, such as Lionel Trilling's Freud and the Crisis of our Culture.
As general editor of the Beacon Contemporary Affairs series, his first eight books were Three Who Made A Revolution by Bertram Wolfe, Homage to Catalonia by George Orwell, The Century of Total War by Raymond Aron,An End to Innocence by Leslie Fiedler, The Need for Roots by Simone Weil, The Hero in History by Sidney Hook, Social Darwinism in American Thought by Richard Hofstadter, and The Invisible Writing by Arthur Koestler. As an editor, Stein shepherded his friend James Baldwin's seminal work Notes of a Native Son to publication in 1955. Stein later documented his editing of the book and his friendship with Baldwin in Native Sons: A Friendship that Created One of the Greatest Works of the Twentieth Century: Notes of a Native Son.
Stein and Baldwin had been friends since attending DeWitt Clinton High School and it was Stein who encouraged Baldwin to assemble Notes of a Native Son. Baldwin's first novel, Go Tell It on the Mountain, was released in 1953 and established Baldwin as one of the most important writers of his generation and his later essays and plays cemented his status as a prominent, young African-American voice. With his wife, Patricia Day, Stein founded the publishing firm Stein and Day in 1962, which was primarily a trade book publisher of popular and literary fiction, biographies, and social histories for a quarter of a century. After a mass-market paperback distributor defaulted on a large payment, Stein and Day sued the distributor, the judge did nothing for four years, and finally Stein and Day, despite substantial orders for many of its books, was forced to close by two competing printers. The publisher’s large and active backlist was sold by creditors to another publisher who did nothing to create the works. Stein detailed the corruption of the American bankruptcy process in a much praised nonfiction book A Feast for Lawyers.
Stein began his career as a novelist with 1969's The Husband, which was based on his earlier play Of Love or Marriage. His greatest success came two years later with The Magician, a dark tale of high school violence that depicts justice as illusionary and lawyers as master magicians (Stein himself is an honorary lifelong member of The International Brotherhood of Magicians). The law proved a productive theme for Stein, with The Magician selling over one million copies. Several of his other novels have legal settings as well. George Thomassy, the suave and talented defense attorney introduced in The Magician continued to work his courtroom magic in Stein's Other People and A Touch of Treason. Stein proved adept at probing the underbelly of white suburban contentment and almost all of his novels mined this vein in some fashion. Stein's published works include The Childkeeper, A Deniable Man, The Resort, Living Room and The Best Revenge: A Novel of Broadway.
Though Stein continued to work on a sequel to The Magician in the early 1990s, as the decade continued he became increasingly devoted to teaching writing at Columbia University, City College of New York, and the University of California, Irvine, and lecturing on writing and publishing at the University of California, Los Angeles, Radcliffe College and Northwestern University. Stein produced two manuals for aspiring writers: Stein on Writing and How to Grow a Novel: The Most Common Mistakes Writers Make and How to Overcome Them, drawing on his own experience as a writer, editor and writing teacher to give advice on constructing compelling narratives. Stein seized upon the growing market for electronic writing manuals and produced and developed software programs for writers including WritePro and FictionMaster. Stein was also commissioned by the Software Publishers’ Association to write a manual for its members, How to Develop a Sound Software Business. Stein's most recent published work was the aforementioned Native Sons: A Friendship that Created One of the Greatest Works of the Twentieth Century: Notes of a Native Son, released in 2004.
Scope and Content
This collection holds the papers of author, editor and publisher, Sol Stein. The bulk of the papers chart Stein's development as a writer and include multiple drafts of his published novels, plays, poems and non-fiction work, with notes and suggestions from Stein and other readers. The collection also contains drafts of currently unpublished materials, including screenplay and theatrical versions of his novels and other projects. Other materials pertain to Stein's work as an editor and include correspondence charting the publication of James Baldwin's Notes of a Native Son, drafts of two Elia Kazan novels on which he worked and multiple student projects he supervised as a writing instructor. This collection also contains Stein's professional and personal correspondence with notable literary figures including Edward Albee, Saul Bellow, Jacques Barzun, Eric Bentley, Elia Kazan, Arthur Miller, Lionel Trilling and Bertram Wolfe.
Stein's public activities in the 1950s as a writer for Voice of America and as Executive Director of The American Committee for Cultural Freedom are also represented, to a lesser extent, in these papers.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in five series.
Series I: Writings, 1952-2000
Sub-series I.1: Fiction, 1952-1995
Sub-series I.2: Nonfiction, 1988-2000
Series II: EditorialConsulting, 1950-2004
Sub-series II.1: Consulting for Published Materials, 1955-2004
Sub-series II.2: Consulting for Unpublished Materials, undated-1998
Sub-series II.3: Beacon Press, 1950-1956
Series III: Organizations, 1951-1962
Sub-series III.1: Voice of America, 1951-1953
Sub-series III.2: American Committee for Cultural Freedom,1952-1958
Sub-series III.3: New Dramatists' Committee, 1954-1962
Sub-series III.4: Mid-Century Book Club, 1959-1961
Series IV: Correspondence, 1943-2002
Series V:Photographs, 1969-2004, undated
Subjects
American Committee for Cultural Freedom.; Mid-Century Book Club; New Dramatists' Committee.; Voice of America (Organization); Baldwin, James, 1924-1987.; Barzun, Jacques, 1907-; Bentley, Eric, 1916-; Kazan, Elia.; Stein, Sol.; Trilling, Diana.; Trilling, Lionel, 1905-1975.; Wolfe, Bertram David, 1896-1977.; Anti-communist movements--New York (State)--New York.
Access Restrictions
Available for faculty, students, and researchers engaged in scholarly publication projects.
Acquisition
Sol Stein, Purchase 2001
Sol Stein, Purchase 1/2006
[Provenance]
Related Material
The Stein and Day Papers (MS#1197)
The American Committee for Cultural Freedom Records, Tamiment 023 Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Elmer Holmes Bobst Library 70 Washington Square South
New York, NY 10012, New York University Libraries.
Finding aid in repository; folder level control.
- Series I: Writings by Sol Stein, 1952-2000
  - Sub-series I.1: Fiction, 1952-1995
    - Antrim’s Money
      - Draft--with Notes, 1958, (3 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 2 to 4)
      - Draft--First, 1958 May (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Draft--Second, 1958 July (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Draft--Second--with Notes, 1958 July (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Draft--Second--Ideas, 1958 July (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Play Breakdown, 1958 July (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - The Best Revenge--Novel
      - Draft--undated (“Notes by Renni Brown”) (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Draft--undated, (2 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 6 to 7)
      - Draft--with Notes, undated, (2 Folders); (‘Early’) (Box 57, Folder 1 to 2)
      - Draft--with Notes, undated, (2 Folders); (“Comments by Nick Mayo”) (Box 57, Folder 3 to 4)
      - Draft--with Notes, undated (Box 58, Folder 1)
      - Draft--Fifth--Incomplete, 1980 November 15 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Draft-- Sixth--with Notes, 1981 February 14 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Draft--Seventh--with Notes, 1981 September 6 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Draft--Eight--Incomplete--with Notes, circa 1980s (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Draft--Unnumbered, 1984 January, (2 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 2 to 3)
      - Draft--Eleventh--with Notes, circa 1980s (Box 58, Folder 2)
      - Draft--Twelfth--with Notes, circa 1980s (Box 58, Folder 3)
      - Draft--Twelfth--with Notes, 1989 July (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Draft--Unnumbered, 1990 September 5 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Galley--with Notes, 1991 February 25 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - The Best Revenge --Screenplay
      - Draft, circa 1990s (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - Draft--with Notes, circa 1990s (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - The Childkeeper--Novel (originally known as Friday, Saturday, Sunday)
      - Synopsis--with Notes, 1973-1974 (Box 56, Folder 4)
      - Draft--with Notes, undated, (3 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 1 to 3)
      - Draft--First, 1973 September (Box 56, Folder 5)
      - Draft--Second, 1974 January (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Draft--Third, 1975 February (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - Draft--Unnumbered, 1975 February (Box 9, Folder 3)
      - Draft--Unnumbered, circa 1975 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Galley--with Notes, 1975, (3 Folders) (Box 10, Folder 2 to 4)
      - Draft--with Notes, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 5)
      - Publicity Materials, 1975 (Box 11, Folder 1)
      - Editorial Correspondence, 1975, (2 Folders) (Box 11, Folder 2 to 3)
      - Reviews--German, 1976-1977 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - The Childkeeper--Play
      - Draft--Incomplete, undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
      - Draft, 1991 July 20 (Box 11, Folder 5)
      - Draft, 1991 August 19 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Deniable Man
      - Draft, circa 1980s (Box 11, Folder 7)
      - Draft--with Notes, circa 1980s (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - The Husband
      - Draft--with Notes, circa 1960s (Box 12, Folder 2)
      - Draft--First, circa 1960s (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - Draft--Returned from Simon & Schuster, 1969 March (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - Draft--with Notes, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - Galley--with Notes, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - Galley--with Notes, 1968, (2 Folders) (Box 14, Folder 1 to 2)
      - Book--with Notes for Screenplay, 1969 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Law
      - Draft--Incomplete--with Notes, circa 1990s, (2 Folders) (Box 15, Folder 7 to 8)
      - Draft, 1995 July 25 (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Draft--with Notes, 1995 August 24 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - The Living Room (also known as The Rest of your Life)
      - Draft, circa 1970s (“Charlie Brieant’s Copy”) (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - Draft--Second--with Notes, 1973 Spring (Box 17, Folder 2)
      - Reviews--German, 1976 (Box 17, Folder 3)
      - Draft--Third, 1973 October (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - The Magician--Novel
      - Draft--with Notes, undated, (“Very Early”) (Box 18, Folder Novel 2)
      - Draft--with Notes, undated, (“Early”) (Box 19, Folder 1)
      - Draft--with Notes, undated (Box 19, Folder 2)
      - Draft--Fragments--with Notes, undated (Box 19, Folder 3)
      - Draft--Fragments--with Notes, undated, (“Early”) (Box 20, Folder 1 to 2)
      - Draft--with Notes, undated (Box 20, Folder 3)
      - Draft--First--with Notes, undated, (2 Folders) (Box 20, Folder 4 to 5)
      - Draft--with Notes, 1969 November 8, (“Renni Brown’s Copy”) (Box 20, Folder 6)
      - Draft--with Notes, 1969 November 8, (“Charlie Brieant’s Copy”) (Box 21, Folder 1)
      - Draft--Returned from Delacorte Press, undated (Box 21, Folder 2)
      - Critiques and Editorial Correspondence, 1971 (Box 21, Folder 3)
      - Press Clippings--German, 1973-1977 (Box 21, Folder 4)
      - 20th Anniversary Materials, 1990 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - The Magician--Screenplay
      - Notes, undated (Box 22, Folder 1)
      - Draft--Incomplete, undated (Box 22, Folder 2)
      - Draft-- with Notes, undated, (2 Folders) (Box 22, Folder 3 to 4)
      - Draft--First--Incomplete, 1972 January 18 (Box 22, Folder 5)
      - Draft--First, 1972 January 18 (Box 22, Folder 6)
      - Draft--First--with Notes, 1972 January 18 (Box 22, Folder 7)
      - Draft--Second, 1990 June 22 (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - Napoleon (also known as The Illegitimist)
      - Cast List from Production, circa 1950s (Box 14, Folder 4)
      - Draft--Fragment, circa 1950s (Box 14, Folder 5)
      - Draft--First-- with Notes, 1952 (Box 14, Folder 6)
      - Draft--Second--with Notes, 1952 (Box 14, Folder 7)
      - Draft, 1952 (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Draft--with Notes, 1954, (2 Folders) (Box 15, Folder 2 to 3)
      - Manuscript, 1954 (Box 15, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence, 1952-1954 (Box 15, Folder 5)
      - Extract--from RIA Review,1956 July (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Of Love and Marriage, a play
      - Draft, 1963 (Box 22, Folder 9)
      - Draft--with Notes, 1963 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Offered Rolls, an Original Screenplay, (originally known as The Hitchhiker, later known as Kin)
      - Draft--First, 1990 July 29 (Box 23, Folder 2)
      - Draft--First, 1990 July 30, (“Uncorrected Version”) (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Other People
      - Preliminary Materials--with Notes, circa 1970s, (2 Folders) (Box 23, Folder 4 to 5)
      - Draft--Incomplete, circa 1970s (Box 56, Folder 6)
      - Draft--First, circa 1970s (Box 24, Folder 1)
      - Draft--Second--Incomplete, circa 1970s (Box 23, Folder 5)
      - Draft--Second-- with Notes, circa 1970s (“Marlee’s Copy”) (Box 24, Folder 2)
      - Draft--Second--with Notes, circa 1970s (“Charlie Brieant’s Copy”) (Box 25, Folder 1)
      - Draft--Second--Chapters 1-33, circa 1970s (Box 25, Folder 2)
      - Draft--Second--Chapters 34-45, circa 1970s (Box 26, Folder 1)
      - Draft--Third, 1977 April (Box 26, Folder 2)
      - Draft--Fourth, 1977 September, (2 Folders) (Box 27, Folder 1 to 2)
      - Draft--Fifth--with Notes, 1978 January (Box 27, Folder 3)
      - Draft--Fifth--with Notes, 1978 January (Box 28, Folder f.1)
      - Draft--Fifth--with Notes, 1978 January, (“Wally’s Copy”) (Box 28, Folder 2)
      - Promotional Materials and Correspondence, 1978 (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - The Resort-- Novel
      - Draft--Fourth--with Notes, 1979 May (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - A Shadow of My Enemy--Play in Two Acts
      - Draft, circa 1950s (Box 29, Folder 2)
      - Draft, 1955 (Box 29, Folder 3)
      - Draft--with Notes, 1955 (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - Top Secret Mission--A Television Play
      - Draft, 1957 September (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - Touch of Treason (previously Thomassy’s Trial)
      - Draft--First--Incomplete, circa 1980s (Box 30, Folder 2)
      - Draft, circa 1980s (“Notes by Richard Marek”) (Box 30, Folder 3)
      - Draft--with Notes, circa 1980s (Box 31, Folder 1)
      - Draft--with Notes, 1982 September 18, (2 Folders) (Box 31, Folder 2 to 3)
      - Draft--with Notes, 1983 February (Box 32, Folder 1)
      - Draft--with Notes, 1984 April (Box 32, Folder 2)
      - Press Quotes, 1985 (Box 32, Folder 3)
      - Publicity Materials, 1985 (Box 32, Folder 4)
    - White Tribes, (previously Animals)
      - Preparatory Notes and Synopsis, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Draft, undated, (“old version”) (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Draft, 1992 September 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Draft, 1994 June 22 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Draft, 1994 November 28 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Draft, 1994 November 28, (“Notes by Shelly Lowenkopf”) (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Draft, 1995 May 31, (“Notes by Shelly Lowenkopf”) (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Draft, 1995 September 24 (Box 33, Folder f.1)
      - Draft--Returned from William Morris Agency, 1995 November 8 (Box 33, Folder 2)
    - Witness--Play in Three Acts (based on the novel by Whittaker Chambers)
      - Draft--with Notes (Box 34, Folder 1)
      - Manuscript, 1955 (Box 34, Folder 2)
  - Sub-series I.II: Nonfiction, 1988-2000
    - Software
      - Fictionmaster--Draft--with Notes, undated (Box 41, Folder 6)
      - Write Pro
        - Teacher Materials--with Notes, undated (Box 41, Folder 7)
        - Draft--Incomplete--with Notes, undated, (2 Folders) (Box 41, Folder 8 to 9)
        - Draft--First Aid Section--with Notes, undated (Box 42, Folder 1)
        - Draft--Lesson Seven--with Notes, undated (Box 42, Folder 2)
        - Draft--Lesson Eight-- with Notes, undated (Box 42, Folder 3)
        - Draft--Lessons Nine and Ten--with Notes, undated, (7 Folders) (Box 42, Folder 4 to 10)
        - Promotional Materials, circa 2000s (Box 42, Folder 11)
    - Books and Manuals
      - A Feast for Lawyers
        - Draft, 1988 October 2 (Box 56, Folder 7)
        - Press Clippings--American, 1989 (Box 56, Folder 8)
      - How to Develop a Sound Software Business
        - Draft--Incomplete--with Notes, circa 1990s, (2 Folders) (Box 46, Folder 4 to 5)
        - Draft--Incomplete--with Notes, circa 1990s (Box 47, Folder 1)
        - Draft--with Notes, circa 1990s, (4 Folders) (Box 47, Folder 2 to 5)
        - Draft--with Notes, circa 1990s (Box 48, Folder 1)
        - Completed Manual, 1994 (Box 48, Folder 2)
        - Correspondence with Alison Reedy, 1994 June 20 (Box 48, Folder 3)
      - Stein on Writing
        - Draft--Incomplete--with Notes, circa 1990s, (2 Folders) (Box 43, Folder 3 to 4)
        - Draft--with Notes, circa 1990s, (3 Folders) (Box 44, Folder 1 to 3)
        - Draft--Incomplete, 1995 (Box 45, Folder 1)
        - Draft, 1995 February, (“Notes by Patricia Day”) (Box 45, Folder 2 to 4)
        - Draft--Chapters 1-14--with Notes, 1995 (Box 45, Folder 5)
        - Draft-- Chapters 15-32--with Notes, 1995 (Box 46, Folder 1)
        - Draft--with Notes, 1995 (Box 46, Folder 2)
        - Press Release, 1995 December 14 (Box 46, Folder 3)
- Series II: Editorial Consulting, 1950-2004
  - Sub-series II.1: Consulting for Published Materials, 1955-2004
    - Baldwin, James
      - Dark Runner--Synopsis for Screenplay, 1958 October 27 (co-authored with Sol Stein) (Box 53, Folder 14)
      - Equal in Paris--Draft, circa 1957 (co-authored with Sol Stein) (Box 53, Folder 15)
      - Notes of a Native Son
        - Correspondence with James Baldwin, 1955-1958 (Box 53, Folder 16)
        - Correspondence with Publishers, 1955-1958 (Box 44, Folder 1)
        - Publicity Materials, 1955 (Box 44, Folder 2)
        - Notes of a Native Son Revisited--, essay by James Baldwin, undated (Box 44, Folder 3)
      - Native Sons, by Sol Stein
        - Graphic Corrections of Baldwin Correspondence, 2000s (Box 44, Folder 4)
        - Draft--Incomplete--with Notes, 2002-2003 (Box 44, Folder 5)